# Tianyi Zhang

zty@seas.upenn.edu | https://tianyi0608.github.io/tianyizhang



#### **HIGHLIGHTS**

**Expertise:** Human Cognition 6 years in B.S., M.Ed.

Natural Language Processing 4 years in MSE and beyond

Research Experience: 4 projects in 4 years: Synopsis:

Event Extraction DARPA BETTER, 20-22, member, publication [5]
Schema Induction DARPA KAIROS, 22-23, leader, publication [1]
Natural to Symbolic Translation AI2, 23, member & leader, publication [2,3]

Pretraining with NL-KG Reconstruction University of Bonn, 24 fall, ongoing

• Research Interests: Reasoning in Natural & Symbolic Language

Other human cognition and NLP related fields

Happy to explore and confident to work well in varied tasks

#### **EDUCATION**

• University of Pennsylvania | Philadelphia, America Sept. 2018 – Dec. 2022

MSE in Data Science GPA: 3.97/4.00

Advisor: Prof. Chris Callison-Burch

M.Ed. in Learning Science and Technology GPA: 3.91/4.00

Advisor: Prof. Yasmin B. Kafai

• **Beijing Normal University** | Beijing, China Sept. 2014 – Jul. 2018

B.S. in Educational Technology GPA: 88/100

Advisor: Prof. Qian Fu

## **PUBLICATIONS**

- [1] Zhang, T., Mai, F., Flek, L., Pretraining Language Models with NL-KG-NL Reconstruction Loop. Paper in writing.
- [2] **Zhang, T.** \*, Zhang, L. \*, Hou, Z., Wang, Z., Gu, Y., Clark, P., Callison-Burch, C., and Tandon, N. (2024). PROC2PDDL: Open-Domain Planning Representations from Texts. In Proceedings of the Second Workshop on Natural Language Reasoning and Structured Explanations (NLRSE) (oral + poster).
- [3] Zhang, L., Jansen, P., **Zhang, T.**, Clark, P., Callison-Burch, C., Tandon, N. (2024). PDDLEGO: Iterative Planning in Textual Environments. In Proceedings of the 13th Joint Conference on Lexical and Computational Semantics (\*SEM).
- [4] Jin, M., Kaul, M., Ramakrishnan, S., Jain, H., Chandrawat, S., Agarwal, I., **Zhang, T.**, Zhu, A., Callison-Burch, C. (2024). WorldWeaver: Procedural World Generation for Text Adventure Games using Large Language Models. In Proceedings of the 4th Wordplay: When Language Meets Games @ ACL 2024.
- [5] **Zhang, T.**\*, Tham, I. \*, Hou, Z. \*, Ren, J., Zhou, L., Xu, H., Zhang, L., Martin, L., Dror, R., Li, S., Ji, H., Palmer, M., Brown, S., Suchocki, R., and Callison-Burch, C. (2023). Human-in-the-Loop Schema Induction. In Proceedings of the 61st Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (Volume 3: System Demonstrations) (poster).
- [6] Zhang, T., Sulem, E., Roth, D. Question-Answering Data Augmentation for Argument Role Labeling.

#### RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

### • Lamarr Institute at University of Bonn

Pretraining Language Model through Unsupervised Text and Knowledge Graph Loop

- To enhance model's understanding and reasoning abilities on downstream tasks
- Design pretraining pipeline imitating human learning: encoding-memorization-decoding
- Train encoder-decoder LMs on masked knowledge tuples and NL-KG-NL reconstruction objectives
- · Improve faithfulness and interpretability of black-box LMs

# • NLP Group at UPenn

May. 2022 - Jun. 2023

Natural to Symbolic Reasoning

- · To reason on events unfold: infer events with fine-grained entity-state
- Translate open-domain Natural Language text (wikiHow) to Symbolic Language (PDDL) with GPT-4
- · Decompose the task into three stages: extraction, inference, and translation
- Identify strong text extraction and entity-state inference abilities with complex wikiHow text (~5000 words)
- · Acknowledge a weak translation capability to predefined symbolic predicates
- Improve the entity-state tracking using CoT and instructions on translation.
- Publication [2][3]: "PROC2PDDL: Towards Open-Domain Symbolic Planning"

#### **Event Schema Induction**

- To understand event relations: (semi-) automatically create event schema in high quality
- Design the scaffolds (cause, plan, procedure, effect, etc.) for GPT-3
- · Apply SRL and constituency parsing to summarize and extract structured events
- · Build schema graphs by adding temporal relations to the events
- · Iteratively prompt LM and merge graphs
- Design interface for human GPT interactive schema generation
- Improve accuracy and efficiency (1 hour to 15 mins per schema) and adopted by the UIUC group
- Publication [1]: "Human-in-the-Loop Schema Induction"

# Cognitive Computation Group at UPenn

Mar. 2020 – Dec. 2022

**Event Extraction** 

- To understand atomic events: extract events with 'who does what to whom'
- Identify and classify event triggers using sequence tagging
- Design a pipeline: BIO identify event type classify model to replace the joint model
- · Improve performance with transfer learning on target language dataset, e.g., OntoNotesArabic
- Identify and classify event arguments using QA
- Design fixed questions for each argument role and convert the argument role labeling task to the Question-Answering task
- Build a pipeline model: has/no answer classification + has answer identification to replace has-and-no-answer joint model
- Improve performance with transfer learning on auxiliary QA datasets, e.g., SQuAD, QAMR

# **Event Data Augmentation**

- To overcome the deficiency of event annotation data
- · Design a pipeline approach: answer extraction (AE) and question generation (QG)
- Train AEwSRL-QG Bert-T5 model to extract QA pairs from unlabeled event text
- Evaluate the augmented data on QA event extraction model
- Prove the effectiveness of the data augmentation approach (8k synthetic data exceeds 80k SQuAD data test on the ACE)
- Publication [5]: "Question-Answering Data Augmentation for Argument Role Labeling"

Sept. 2024 -

# WORK EXPERIENCE

•	Visiting Scholar	Lamarr Institute   University of Bonn, Germany Advised by Prof. Lucie Flek	Sept. 2024 – Dec. 2024
		See the Research Experience section for details	
•	Research Assistant	NLP Group   University of Pennsylvania, America See the Research Experience section for details	May. 2022 – Jun. 2023
		Cognitive Computation Group   University of Pennsylvania	Mar. 2020 – Dec. 2022
		See the Research Experience section for details	
•	Teaching Assistant	CIS522 Deep Learning   University of Pennsylvania, America	Jan. 2022 – May. 2022
		Design course materials and teach deep learning models in CV, NLP, RL, etc.	
		· Hold Office Hours and group discussions each week.	
•	Data Analyst	SciStarter   Philadelphia, America	Sep. 2018 – Apr. 2019
		Use the Python Pandas package to clean and analyze email log-in data (30,000 records).	
		Find the highest possibility of emails being checked is between 9 a.m. to 3 p.m., and within 1 day (over 80%). The most attractive topics are love, games, and high tech. The royalty of the subscriber is 50%.	